



Micaela Romanini

Date of birth: 27/12/1986 | **Nationality:** Italian | **Phone number:**

(+39) 3473751311 (Mobile) | **Email address:** roma.micaela@gmail.com

Address: Ciampino, 00043, Rome, Italy (Home)

ABOUT ME

Born in Darmstadt, Germany.

I am a Professional with over 12 years of experience in Digital (applied to Games, Education, Culture) and a background in Communications, covering skills and expertise in the areas of Integrated Marketing Communications, Events Management, Partnerships Management, Project Management and Business Development.

I authorize the processing of personal data contained in my curriculum vitae based on art. 13 of Legislative Decree no. 196/2003 and art. 13 GDPR (EU Regulation 2016/679)

WORK EXPERIENCE

01/04/2023 - CURRENT

EXPERT EVALUATOR EIT CULTURE & CREATIVITY

Expert Evaluator for the Knowledge and Innovation Community (KIC) on Culture & Creativity of the European Institute of Innovation and Technology (EIT).

01/03/2023 - CURRENT

EXTERNAL EXPERT EVALUATOR - CREATIVE EUROPE MEDIA - VIDEOGAME AND IMMERSIVE CONTENT CALL 2023 EUROPEAN COMMISSION

08/01/2018 - CURRENT Rome, Italy

FOUNDER AND DIRECTOR WOMEN IN GAMES ITALIA

- Events Strategic planning to educate about Diversity and Inclusion, targeting Companies, Schools and Institutions
- Liasing with International Organization Women in Games WIGJ to run Local and International Campaigns
- Liasing with Partners to organize campaigns; events
- Run Studies and Research projects, partnering with national/global stakeholders
- Create and Oversee Communication strategies and Brand Reputation Management; disseminate communications content to key audiences and stakeholders.
- Plan strategic communications campaigns to support organizational goals and monitor KPIs
- Oversee design, contents and messaging in communication, marketing and event materials, including website, social media, video and audio content.
- Ensure compliance to WIGJ brand guidelines and provide training to internal teams on its implementation.
- Oversee event management and planning from concept to execution (online and in-person events)

Events organized \ attended as spokeperson:

- Attended as Speaker: Women in Esports A Discussion Paper to summarise and address the underrepresentation of women in all aspects of esports. GLOBAL ESPORTS FORUM, MARCH 1, 2018 Katowice
- Attended as Speaker: European Youth Event, an event promoted by the European Parliament on 1 and 2 June 2018. I've joined the panel "Video games meet heritage: Young digital creators for Europe's cultural assets, organized in collaboration with the Directorate-General for Education, Youth, Sport and Culture of the European Commission to talk about the issue of diversity in the videogames sector http://www.europarl.europa.eu/european-youth-event/en/home/home.htmlPREVIOUS

- Organiser and Moderator for the Conference Women in Gaming: The Next Generation, with the English Embassy in Rome and the UK Science & Innovation Network, which was introduced by the English Ambassador in Italy Jill Morris on 20 November 2018
- Italian localization and Press Event Organization for the release of the guide "BUILDING A FAIR PLAYING FIELD". Created with the aim of sharing good practices in the field of gender equality in the video game sector, the guide is a useful tool for making work environments increasingly inclusive and open to representing diversity. The document places the Women's Empowerment Principles of the United Nations at the center of the ethical project is an Italian adaptation of the international guide created by Women in Games with the support of the European federation Interactive Software Federation of Europe (ISFE), IIDEA, InGAME.

31/05/2022 - CURRENT Rome, Italy

DIRECTOR OF BUSINESS DEVELOPMENT GLOBALSTEP

- Develop strategies and actionable solutions to improve performance, seize opportunities and grow business
- · Communication, Brand Management, and Evangelization targeting the EMEA Region
- Target Market Engagement for Lead Generation (EMEA)
- Strategic planning of Events (including sponsorships) to increase Branding and Reputation and develop business (Global and EMEA)
- Manage Relationships (from prospecting and outreach to new account acquisition and Sales)
- Prepare activity reports.

01/12/2016 - 30/05/2022 Roma, Italy

VD, BUSINESS DEVELOPMENT, MARKETING AND COMMUNICATIONS VIGAMUS FOUNDATION

- Manage and oversee the Foundation's products and business units strategic development
- Plan and execute Corporate and Integrated marketing communications campaigns (engaging stakeholders, partners and decision makers)
- Oversee Communications, Marketing and sales teams to launch Events and Educational Programs in the Region. Coordinate Career Days and Open Days planning and Communications
- Work with local and global Institutions and Companies to execute international projects (ex EU Parliament and Commission
- Develop Integrated Marketing campaigns

Events organized on behalf of EFGAMP and VIGAMUS Foundation:

- Cultural heritage in Europe: linking past and future ": Event, 26 June 2018. Organized the exhibition "Exhibition on the History of the Video Game", the VIGAMUS Foundation and EFGAMP participated in the European Parliament in Brussels to enhance the cultural and artistic identity of the interactive medium.
- "Video games meet heritage: Young digital creators for Europe's cultural assets": panel dedicated to the European Youth Event, 2 June 2018. Organized with the Directorate General for Education and Culture of the European Commission on behalf of VIGAMUS Foundation, EFGAMP and WIG Italia, I've also participated in the panel to evaluate video games as part of cultural heritage, also evaluating issues related to diversity and inclusion in the games industry.
- Event organized with the EU Commission: "Our Heritage, Where the past meets the Future": Game Jam at the European Culture Forum, 7-8 December 2017. The Game Jam organized during the European Culture Forum 2017 brought together young video game creators from all over Europe. For 25 hours they undertook to transform the theme of the European Year of Cultural Heritage into a video game, entitled "Our Heritage, Where the past meets the Future".
- Event organized with the Swiss Embassy in Italy and VIGAMUS Foundation: "Taking Gaming to the Next Level" event at the VIGAMUS Videogame Museum. An overview of the video game industry in Switzerland and Italy, with its opportunities and challenges, in collaboration with important institutions and companies in the sector. The event was opened by: Deputy Ambassador of Switzerland, Michele Coduri, Undersecretary of State, Anna Ascani, Ministry of Economic Development.
- Delegation of the European Union in Mexico, "Interactive solutions for education, culture and museums". Event organized Representing EFGAMP - the European Federation of Videogame Archives, Museums and preservation projects. Among the speakers: Lorena Aldana-Ortega, European Policy Coordinator, Europa Nostra, Juergen Bänsch, Director Policy and Public Affairs, ISFE, Harmke Heezen, High Road Studios, Germany, Lisa Lindén, Doris Film, Sweden, Elisa Navarro, Gargamel Estudio, Mexico, Roberto López Díaz, Siete Media, Mexico. The event was moderated by Cristina Novio, EU-MX SDSF Team Leader

PROFESSOR "INTEGRATED MARKETING COMMUNICATIONS" AND "DIVERSITY AND INCLUSION POLICIES" LINK CAMPUS UNIVERSITY

Professor, Integrated Marketing Communications in the Entertainment Industries

Modules:

- The basic principles of communication
- Corporate Reputation and Communication
- CSR Corporate Social Responsibility
- Event Management
- Experience marketing
- Integrated Marketing Communications strategies

Professor, "Diversity and Inclusion Policies in the Games Industry"

Modules:

- · Digital Gender Gap: data analysis
- · Diversity in Business
- Leadership schemes
- Monocultural, Pluricultural and Multicultural Companies
- Games Studies: Gamers' motivation by genres
- · Case History: Gamergate
- · Women in Games; Women in eSports

01/06/2012 - 30/05/2022

COMMUNICATIONS AND EVENTS DIRECTOR EFGAMP EUROPEAN FEDERATION OFF GAMES ARCHIVES, MUSEUMS AND PRESERVATION PROJECTS

- Coordinate Partners and project management (European Calls and funded projects, Horizon 2020)
- · Content writing: website, flyers, promotional materials, social media
- · Media and Public Relations Management;
- Events Management: Exhibitions and panels organized with EU Institutions
- Formulate, oversee and execute communication strategies
- Plan strategic communications campaigns and define KPIs to monitor their reception and performance
- · Oversee design, contents and messaging in communication, marketing and event materials
- Prepare media activity reports.
- Develop Integrated Marketing campaigns (video, newsletters, social media, graphic and viral marketing)

01/08/2017 - 01/01/2020 Roma, Italy

EVENT DIRECTOR GAMEROME

- Manage Programme (from inviting speakers to organizing roundtables with EU institutions EU Commission)
- Oversee Promotion sales (sponsored activities)
- Develop and cultivate International partnerships (Institutions, trade organizations, EU Institutions)
- Communities and stakeholders engagement
- Budget allocation and management
- Plan and execute Marketing Activities and Communication strategies
- Market research, analyze data and forecast on results
- Work with media agencies, paid agencies and PR agencies
- Oversee event management and planning from concept to execution (for all the 3 years duration of the event).
- Manage external providers (audiovisual services, venues, catering)
- Create and oversee Integrated Marketing campaigns

Most relevant Achievements:

In 3 years, the event was positioned as the main International B2B event in Italy for Games and Digital Entertainment, counting over 600 attendees globally (including Japan, Korea, LATAM, US) and leading Companies in Technology and Entertainment (Bandai Namco Entertainment, Hewlett Packard Enterprise, Microsoft, Koch Media, King, Nintendo, Square Enix, Ubisoft)

XBOX.COM INTERNATIONAL COORDINATOR MICROSOFT

- Responsible for coordinating the Xbox.com International team in the delivery of local and global marketing campaigns and content;
- Coordination of digital campaigns partnering with regional Xbox marketing teams in 44 markets (APAC, LATAM, EMEA and UAE)
- Support the International Lead and Campaign Manager in executing large scale International, regional, market and global projects including E3 and Gamescom;
- Oversee market approvals across all globally lead activities, executing outbound communications
- Create and execute partnerships and marketing campaigns
- Manage agencies to design, localise and adapt global campaigns for local markets
- Create Integrated Marketing campaigns (video, newsletters, social media, graphic and viral marketing)
- Project planning and management
- Data analysis, forecast, and report on campaign objectives.

01/06/2012 - 01/04/2016 Roma, Italy

DIGITAL MARKETING AND CONTENT MANAGER VIGAMUS FOUNDATION

- Digital Marketing strategy planning and management (Content, Social Media Marketing-including a over 70.000 likes Facebook page- SEO, Analytics, Email Marketing, A/B Testing, PPC - Google Adwords, Facebook Ads - Affiliate Marketing campaigns)
- Monitor performance (Google Analytics, KPIs, statistics analysis, reports, customers feedback, website and social media subscribers, site hits etc.)
- · Advertising and Promotion campaigns on traditional/digital media
- Planning and Management of Exhibitions and Events (either Consumer and Cultural)
- Press Releases and Communication
- Partnerships Development and Business Relations management: International Companies (USA, Europe and Japan)
- Representative at International Game Fairs and Events (Gamescom_Cologne; E3_LA_US; Tokyo Game Show_JP)
- Research Center Coordinator, Interns Coordination and tutoring

Most relevant Achievements:

- "E.T. The Fall" Exhibition: the VIGAMUS Museum secured a world wide premiere exclusive of the Atari buried findings in Alamogordo, items received in permanent donation on October 20th, 2014. I managed the exhibition's planning and promotion: the event received International press coverage including the industry leader website Polygon and has been then followed by few relevant museums (The Smithsonian, Dec.'14)
- Museum's weekly visitors rate increased by 30% (200 to 500 units) while monthly visitors rate increased by 40% (from 800 to 2000 visitors) in one year thanks to digital marketing strategy and activities plan.
- VIGAMUS Academy Courses got acknowledged as a leading Education Program on Games and digital entertainment by the Ministry of Education in Italy.

11/02/2011 - 11/05/2011 Roma, Italy

PRESS AND COMMUNICATION OFFICER TEATRO SISTINA

- Social Media Marketing;
- Content writing: website, flyers, promotional materials
- · Media and Public Relations Management;
- Events Management: Press Conferences and Preview Events.
- Prepare media activity reports.

EDUCATION AND TRAINING

02/08/2023 - 02/09/2023

PROJECT MANAGEMENT EU Academy

Website https://academy.europa.eu/courses/pm-c1-pm-essentials-project-management-methodology

01/05/2023 - CURRENT Rome, Italy

SUSTAINABILITY DEVELOPMENT: CULTURAL, ECOLOGICAL AND DIGITAL TRANSITION Sapienza Università di Roma

Website https://www.uniroma1.it/en/offerta-formativa/corso-di-formazione/2023/le-scienze-della-sostenibilita-la-transizione-culturale

01/03/2021 - CURRENT

MBA ECONOMICS AND COMMUNICATIONS FOR MANAGEMENT AND INNOVATION University of Rome Sapienza

Website https://corsidilaurea.uniroma1.it/en/corso/2021/31296/home

Brussels, Belgium

INTERNATIONAL DEVELOPMENT AND THE EUROPEAN UNION PROFESSIONAL COURSE European Leadership University

Modules:

- Introduction to International Development

Mapping Existing Tools of EU's External Relations and Development

- International Trade and Development
- National Branding and Global Development
- Development and Gender
- Global Migration and Development
- Introduction to Project Management
- Climate Change and International Development
- Global Hunger, Poverty and Unemployment
- Overview of International Organisations and Career Opportunities

Field of study Political sciences and civics

DIGITAL MARKETING PROFESSIONAL CERTIFICATE Shaw Academy UK and Ireland

Website https://www.shawacademy.com/

01/05/2010 - 01/05/2012 Rome, Italy

MASTER'S DEGREE IN "COMMUNICATION, INFORMATION SCIENCES AND MARKETING" University of Rome Tor Vergata

Website https://web.uniroma2.it/

01/10/2006 - 10/03/2010 Rome, Italy

BACHELOR'S DREGREE IN "COMMUNICATION SCIENCES AND JOURNALISM" University of Rome Tor Vergata

Website www.uniroma2.it

LANGUAGE SKILLS

Mother tongue(s): **ITALIAN**

Other language(s):

	UNDERSTANDING		SPEAKING		WRITING
	Listening	Reading	Spoken production	Spoken interaction	
ENGLISH	C1	C1	C1	C1	C1
SPANISH	B2	B2	B2	B2	B2
GERMAN	B1	B1	B1	B1	B1

	UNDERSTANDING		SPEAKING		WRITING
	Listening	Reading	Spoken production	Spoken interaction	
JAPANESE	B1	B1	B1	B1	B1

Levels: A1 and A2: Basic user; B1 and B2: Independent user; C1 and C2: Proficient user

DIGITAL SKILLS

Microsoft Office | Microsoft Word | Microsoft Excel | Microsoft Powerpoint | Social Media | Power Point | Good listener and communicator | Organizational and planning skills | Decision-making | Team-work oriented | Analytical skills | Creativity | Critical thinking | Strategic Planning | Presenting | Ability to Work Under Pressure | Conflict resolution | Good time management | Flexibility | Detail-Oriented